because I want to ask you a couple of questions. I think many here, and in general in Western countries, would agree with your statement about analysis of democratic systems becoming dysfunctional, but at the same time, many would kind of find unsettling the thought that there is an unelected authority that, without any form of oversight or consultation, decides what the national interest is. What is the mechanism in the Chinese model that allows people to say, actually, the national interest as you defined it is wrong? EXL: You know, Frank Fukuyama, the political scientist, called the Chinese system "responsive authoritarianism." It's not exactly right, but I think it comes close. So I know the largest public opinion survey company in China, okay? Do you know who their biggest client is? The Chinese government. Not just from the central government, the city government, the provincial government, to the most local neighborhood districts. They conduct surveys all the time. Are you happy with the garbage collection? Are you happy with the general direction of the country? So there is, in China, there is a different kind of mechanism to be responsive to the demands and the thinking of the people. My point is, I think we should get unstuck from the thinking that there's only one political system -- election, election, election -- that could make it responsive. I'm not sure, actually, elections produce responsive government anymore in the world. (Applause) BG: Many seem to agree. One of the features of a democratic system is a space for civil society to express itself. And you have shown figures about the support that the government and the authorities have in China. But then you've just mentioned other elements like, you know, big challenges, and there are, of course, a lot of other data that go in a different direction: tens of thousands of unrests and protests and environmental protests, etc. So you seem to suggest the Chinese model doesn't have a space outside of the Party for civil society to express itself. EXL: There's a vibrant civil society in China, whether it's environment or what-have-you. But it's different. You wouldn't recognize it. Because, by Western definitions, a so-called civil society has to be separate or even in opposition to the political system, but that concept is alien for Chinese culture. For thousands of years, you have civil society, yet they are consistent and coherent and part of a political order, and I think it's a big cultural difference. BG: Eric, thank you for sharing this with TED. EXL: Thank you.
parce que je veux vous poser deux ou trois questions. Je pense que nombreux sont ici, et de manière générale dans les pays occidentaux, ceux qui seraient d'accord avec votre affirmation que les systèmes démocratiques deviennent dysfonctionnels, mais en même temps, nombreux sont ceux qui trouveraient troublante l'idée qu'une autorité non élue, sans aucune forme de supervision ni consultation décide de l'intérêt national. Quel est le mécanisme du modèle chinois qui permet aux gens de dire qu'en fait l'intérêt national comme on le définit chez nous est erroné ? EXL : Eh bien, le politologue, Frank Fukuyama, a qualifié le système chinois « d'autoritarisme réactif ». Ça n'est pas tout à fait exact, mais je pense que ça en est proche. Je connais le plus grand institut de sondage de Chine, d'accord ? Savez-vous quel est leur plus gros client ? Le gouvernement chinois. Et non pas seulement le gouvernement central, mais aussi le gouvernement municipal , le gouvernement provincial, et même les mairies de quartiers. Ils mènent des enquêtes d'opinion tout le temps. Êtes-vous satisfait de la collecte des ordures ? Êtes-vous satisfait de la direction générale du pays ? Donc en Chine, il y a une autre sorte de mécanisme pour être attentif aux demandes et aux opinions des gens. Ce que je veux dire, c'est qu'il faut qu'on se libère de la pensée selon laquelle il n'y a qu'un seul système politique -- élections, élections, élections -- qui puisse faire en sorte d’être attentif aux opinions des citoyens. En fait, je pense que les élections n'engendrent plus de gouvernements attentifs dans le monde. (Applaudissements) BG : Ils sont nombreux à être d'accord apparemment. L'un des attributs du système démocratique est l’espace d’expression attribuer à la société civile. Et vous avez illustré, chiffres à l'appui, le soutien dont le gouvernement et les autorités bénéficient en Chine. Mais vous avez mentionné d'autres éléments tels que, les grands défis, et il y a bien sûr une grande quantité de données qui vont dans un autre sens : des dizaines de milliers d'agitations et de protestations et des protestations sur l'environnement, etc... Ainsi, votre discours pourrait laisser entendre que le modèle chinois n'offre pas d'espace en dehors du Parti pour que la société civile s'exprime. EXL : Il y a une société civile dynamique en Chine, qu'il s'agisse de l'environnement ou de toute autre chose. Mais elle est différente. Parce que, selon les définitions occidentales, une société civile doit nécessairement être indépendante ou carrément dans l'opposition au système politique, mais ce concept est étranger à la culture chinoise. Depuis des milliers d'années, une société civile existe bien qu'elle soit compatible et cohérente et fasse partie d'un ordre politique, et je crois qu'il faut y voir là une grande différence culturelle. BG : Eric, merci d'avoir partagé avec TED. EXL : Merci.